http://youtu.be/FnG0vOYMu3Q
phungdo_vgu
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So now that we understand the laws and the
DR. YERRABALLI: Giờ ta đã hiểu luật và
terminology, let's look at a couple of concepts that are going to be repeated
thuật ngữ, hãy nhìn vào các khái niệm mà sẽ được lặp lại khá
quite often.
thường xuyên.
The first thing is the idea of voltage division, or voltage divider.
Đầu tiên là ý niệm về phân  chia điện áp, hay bộ phân áp.
The idea of voltage division is that when I have an element-- here's a
Sự phân chia điện áp là khi tôi có một yếu tố-- đây là một
resistance, a second resistance--
điện trở, một điện trở thứ hai--
and we have two points a and b.
tôi có hai điểm a và b.
Let's call this ab, and this is positive, negative.
gọi chiều a-b là dương , ngược là âm.
So we have a voltage Vab, which we just applied across these two
ta có điện áp Vab, nó là ta vừa áp dụng đi qua hai
conductors or resistors.
các tụ hoặc các điện trở.
And we said, let's say these are resistance R1 and R2.
ta xem, đây là điện trở R1 và R2
And we say that we are connecting these in series.
Ta đang mắc chúng nối tiếp.
The idea of connecting elements in series is that they
Cách mắc nối tiếp là các phần tử cùng
share a common point.
có một điểm mắc chung.
That is the idea of connecting two elements in series.
Đó là ý tưởng của việc mắc mạch nối tiếp.
So this element here and this element here have a common point.
Phần tử ở đây và ở đây cùng mắc chung một điểm.
So there, we say that they are in series.
Vậy thì, ta xem đó là mắc nối tiếp.
Now, a series connection of elements creates what we
Cách mắc mạch nối tiếp tạo ra
call as voltage divider.
bộ phân áp.
That is, the voltage ab is divided between the first element, R1, and the
Điện áp Vab bị phân ra giữa điện trở R1 và
second element, R2.
điện trở R2.
So we say that there is a voltage drop here at V1, a voltage drop here at V2,
Ta xem rằng có một sự sụt áp ở V1, một sự sụt áp ở V2,
and there's a plus, minus, plus, minus.
Nó có một dương, âm dương, âm
And we have our current, I. So since they share a common point, the same
Cường độ dòng điện, I. Vì chúng mắc chung một điểm nên có cùng
current flows through both of these resistances.
dòng điện I đi qua cả hai điện trở.
So one of the things we often like to think of is drawing this as an
Thứ tôi thường vẽ là mạch điện tương đương
equivalent circuit.
equivalent circuit.
We say that this is same as the circuit ab, with
Xem đây giống với mạch điện ab với điện
the voltage ab applied.
áp Vab được đặt vào.
And this is my current.
Đây là dòng điện I.
And This is the equivalent circuit.
Đây là mạch điện tương đương.
What this tells us is that the equivalent resistance, R, is given by
Nó cho ta biết điện trở tương đương - R, tính bằng
R1 plus R2.
R1 + R2
This is what connecting them in series will give us.
Khi mắc nối tiếp thì đó là thứ ta có.
What we also know is that the total drop from a to b is going to be, which
Ta biết rằng, toàn bộ sự giảm điện thế từ a đến b là Vab
is Vab, is equal to the drop across the first one plus the drop across the
Vab bằng với sự giảm điện thế khi qua R1 cộng với sự giảm điện thế khi
second one.
qua R2.
So by combining these two equations, and the fact that the same I flows
Kết hợp hai phương trình
through them, we can say that V1 is given by R1 divided by R1
ta có V1 tính bằng R1 chia R1+R2
plus R2 times Vab.
nhân Vab.
And V2 is given by R2 by R1 plus R2 times Vab, which means that the
V2 tính bằng R2 chia R1+R2 nhân Vab, nghĩa là
voltage drop across any of these resistance is proportional to the
Sụt áp qua các điện trở tỉ lệ thuận với
resistance R1 divided by the total equivalent resistance.
điện trở R1, với mẫu là tổng trở tương đương.
So these are things that we should remember.
Đó là những điều cần nhớ.
So that voltage divider does that.
Bộ chia điện áp làm điều đó.
This is the equivalent resistance of a voltage divider.
Đây là điện trở tương đương của bộ chia điện áp.
Now, let's take a look at what happens if you connect elements in parallel.
Cùng xem qua điều gì xảy ra khi mắc mạch song song.
So if I connect two elements in parallel, so here's my Element R1 and
Nếu tôi nối 2 phần tử song song, đây là điện trở  R1 và
Element R2.
điện trở R2.
And here we have, again, a voltage, so this is my Point a and Point b.
Tôi đang có một hiệu điện thế Đây là điểm a và điểm b.
So we have a voltage Vab, which is, by the way, the same voltage across these
Ta có điện áp Vab, Điện áp hai đầu mỗi điểm là cũng bằng
two points, also.
nhau.
And we have a current I.
Có một dòng điện I.
Now, I is going to split between these two paths, I1 and I2.
I bị chia thành 2 dòng giữa 2 đường, I1 và I2.
You can think of this as water flowing along a path.
Tưởng tượng như dòng nước chảy qua 1 con đường.
And there are two possible paths to the water.
Trên đây thì có 2 đường chảy cho dòng nước.
Some of the water is going to go this path, and some water is going to take
Có nước chảy đường này có nước chảy đường kia.
the other path.
.
Now, in this case, the amount of water, and again, here that's
Trường hợp này, lượng nước chính là
equivalent to current, the amount of current that flows through R1 and R2
tương đương với dòng điện. Cường độ dòng điện đi qua R1 và R2
can be calculated based on what the values of R1 and R2 are.
có thể được tính dựa vào giá trị của R1 và R2.
Let's see what this one looks like in its equivalent form.
Nhìn xem cái này có giống dạng tương tương của nó.
So we say that this is the equivalent resistance R. And this is, again, ab.
Đây là điện trở tương đương R, Lại một lần nữa, giữa a - b.
And this is our current, I.
Cường độ dòng điện, I.
So on the equivalent resistance R, when we have parallel connection,
Điện trở tương đương R khi ta mắc mạch song song.
again, the idea of parallel connection is that they share
Ý tưởng của mạch điện song song là chúng
two points in common.
có 2 điểm chung.
That is, the two endpoints, so R1 and R2 have the same endpoints.
Đó là 2 điểm đầu cuối, R1 và R2 có 2 điểm đầu cuối chung.
So they're connected in parallel.
Chúng được mắc song song.
R is now given by R1, R2 by R1 plus R2.
R được tính bằng R1 * R2 chia  R1 + R2.
This is simply another way of writing 1 by R equals 1 by R1 plus 1 by R2.
Cách viết đơn giản khác là 1/R bằng 1/R1 + 1/R2.
What we also see is that the voltage across this, V1 and V2
Ta thấy được điện áp đi qua chúng V1 và V2
are really the same.
là bằng nhau.
So V1 equals V2 equals Vab.
=> V1 = V2 = Vab.
And this should be obvious to you.
Bạn nên hiểu rõ điều này.
Because the voltage across the Element R1 is a voltage between these two
Vì hiệu điện thế đi qua điện trở R1 là điện áp giữa 2 đầu
points, which is also known to be Vab.
điểm, nó cũng là Vab.
The voltage across this is the voltage across these two points, which is also
Điện áp này là hiệu điện thế giữa hai điểm, cũng được xem
known to be Vab.
là Vab.
Now, what we know is I is equal to I1 plus I2, because
Ta đều biết dòng điện chính I bằng I1 + I2, vì
the current is divided.
dòng điện bị phân ra.
And we can also write, based on these equations, we can write that I1 is
Ta có thể viết, dựa trên các phương trình này, thì I1 tính bằng
given by R2 divided by R1 plus R2 times I. And I2 is R1 divided by R1
R2 chia R1+R2 nhân cho I. I2 bằng R1 chia cho R1+R2
plus R2 times I.
R2 nhân I.
So this is different from our voltage division.
Nó khác với sự phân chia điện áp.
This is our current division.
Đây là sự phân chia dòng điện.
And current division says that the current is divided into two parts, if
Sự phân chia dòng điện chỉ ra dòng điện bị chia thành hai phần, nếu
there are two parts.
có 2 đường.
And the current is determined by the relative voltages.
Dòng điện được xác định bằng quan hệ điện áp.
I1 is based on R2 in the numerator.
I1 có R2 là tử số.
And I2 is based on R1 in the numerator.
I2 thì có R1 là tử số.
Something to remember, because this is a very common mistake students make.
Cần nhớ rằng, đây là sai lầm mà sinh viên thường mắc phải.
So to summarize then, when we are working with parallel circuits, we
Tổng quan thì, khi xử lý mạch song song, ta có
have current division.
sự phân chia dòng điện.
This is the equivalent resistance.
Đây là điện trở tương đương.
And current is equivalently divided in these ratios.
Cường độ dòng điện được phân tương ứng trong các tỉ lệ trên.